[Music]
Hi everyone, welcome back to another
episode of the USADA pitch where we
explore news projects and changes in the
anti-doping world. Today we're talking
about a recent study on the substances
that are used to promote growth of
livestock in the United States. So these
substances are often prohibited in sport
but may remain in trace amounts in
meats. I'm joined today by our chief
science officer, Dr. Matt Fedoric, who
is very familiar with the study due to
his involvement, and he can help explain
more about the research and why it's so
important to athletes. So, welcome,
Matt. Thanks, Avery. It's great to be
back on the pitch with you. Yes, I'm
thrilled to have you and to be talking
about this important study. So, to
begin, what sparked this research?
Yeah, as the listeners may know that
anabolic agents that appear on the
prohibited list may also be used in the
animal husbandry or meat production
industry. Um, and they may be used
legally or illegally depending on the
country. Um, and these residues, as you
mentioned in your intro, may appear in
meat and can lead to positive
anti-doping tests. So our goal with this
study was really to try to understand in
the United States what these residue
levels may uh how they may occur, what
they are in the retail food supply. And
as you know the US geographical area is
quite large. So we wanted to get a
sampling from across the United States
to try to understand if we could detect
these in the retail meat supply.
That's awesome. Um it's a it's an
important topic and can you dig in a
little bit more into who was involved in
um this big of a study and what were
some of the key considerations as you
were developing the parameters and um
making sure that you checked all the uh
te's and gotted all the eyes. Yeah, this
study was funded by the partnership for
clean competition and this was a really
important research collaboration between
uh Texas Tech University. So there's an
expert in meat biology and muscle
biology there. His name is Dr. Bradley
Johnson as well as the UCLA Olympic
Analytical Laboratory Ellie Erenss and
his team there that they analyze athlete
samples and they were involved as a
collaborator in this project. The
project uh went on for over a year. It
actually is also continuing. Um, and we
were really aiming to, as I mentioned,
try to try to find whether these
expected veterinary drug residues may be
present in meat. Um, and we also were
looking for unexpected anabolic agents.
So, we expanded our scope beyond just
what we may expect to see and we were
looking for additional anabolic agents
that appear on the prohibited list as
well. The retail food supply is
obviously the most relevant because uh
athletes may be buying meat from various
grocery stores or or other suppliers.
And so we were able to collect over 50
samples and analyze them for residues.
Wow. All right. So, can you talk us
through the findings and what they mean
for athletes, what they can take away
from this? Yeah, great question. So we
analyzed for for a whole whole menu of
prohibited substances but in the United
States there are a couple of substances
that are legal to be used in in meat
production. So those substances are
trenalone as well as ratopamine and we
did find low levels of both of those in
a small percentage of the meat that that
we sampled. they were far below the
maximum residue limits that are set by
the US Department of Agriculture and
these substances are uh monitored and
there are rules around their use and uh
the way that they're administered to
animals and so these findings were
consistent with what we expected. our
detection sensitivity was extremely high
but um importantly the levels were far
below what kind of maximum residue
limits are are permitted in meat. In
addition, we didn't find any unexpected
or illegal growth promoters in the meat.
So that was comforting as well. The
project is ongoing. We want to sample a
larger sample size and we also want to
look at uh different retail and
wholesale meats that may be imported
into the US from other countries because
this is an ongoing concern. There are
certain suppliers or countries that are
permitted to export meat to the United
States. So we want to get an idea of
there if there's any additional risks
there. Yeah. So bottom line from phase
one of the study, is this new good news
for athletes? I think it's good news for
athletes. It it gives us comfort that we
didn't find in the s in the meat
sampling that we did any extremely high
levels that would be we would consider
of extreme risk to athletes. Obviously,
we want to expand the sample size. As
you know, there's probably tens or
hundreds of thousands of grocery stores
around the United States. So this was a
relatively small initial sample size. So
we were continuing the project. We also
want to look at different organs. So uh
not just uh muscle but we want to look
in in liver as well and some organs to
try to understand how the levels may
vary depending on the different kinds of
meat that are available. And so uh we're
really looking forward to kind of phase
two of this project and ongoing. We did
publish the initial findings. So it is
uh available for in the public
peer-reviewed domain a paper around this
uh particular issue. Yeah. And we'll
make sure to share that out too. All
right. With all this in mind, what's the
guidance at this point for athletes both
in the US and when they're traveling
internationally?
Yeah. In the United States, our guidance
to athletes is that the US meat supply
is extremely safe and a positive test
from consuming meat would be exceedingly
rare. So from a risk perspective, I
think the risk is very low. Athletes can
further reduce their risk by consuming
hormone free meat or organic meat. So,
we would encourage athletes if they're
eating beef, chicken, um, or or pork to
look for those labels on the packaging
that it's raised hormone free. And then
when athletes are traveling to other
countries, particularly high-risk
countries, China, Guatemala, Mexico,
where there has been problems, we we
advise athletes to keep a food log of
where they've eaten. um even take
pictures of what they've eaten as well
as avoid eating in high-risk areas. So,
don't eat meat off of the street, off of
food stalls. And you can also consider
um eating alternative protein sources.
So, you could eat uh nut-based protein
sources or even take your own uh protein
sources while you travel in order to to
further reduce your risk. when athletes
are traveling to the European Union,
they have very strict uh hormone use
controls there. So, the risks are uh
extremely low in countries in Europe.
So, athletes I I think they don't need
to worry when they travel to Europe. And
I think just worth um doubling back on,
it's the
organbased and exotic meats that are
most troublesome abroad. Yeah. So, I
would avoid eating meats that that
you're not used to or eating liver or
other organ derived meats because these
organs tend to concentrate uh toxins or
residues. So, avoid those and and focus
on, you know, normal uh muscle tissue,
uh chicken breast, th those types of
meat, steaks that um aren't organ
derived. Awesome. Well, I think we can
wrap up on that. Thank you so much,
Matt.
Yeah, thanks very much Avery. Pleasure
to be back on the pitch today. Awesome.
Well, stay tuned everyone for more
episodes of the USADA pitch coming soon.
[Music]